Finding Aid for Library Extension Service (University of Michigan) records, 1916-1980
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Library Extension Service (University of Michigan) records 1916-1980
University of Michigan. Library Extension Service.
2 linear feet
87229 Bimu C430 2
University of Michigan unit established to coordinate loan of library materials to high schools and various local organizations, and to supplement the program of the Extension Service. Administrative files, including historical material, annual and monthly reports, and subject files; and published material consisting of bulletins, and printed reading lists and bibliographies.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received from the University Library in May, 1982 (donor no. 1278 ).
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
At the request of William Warner Bishop the Regents authorized the establishment of the Library Extension Service (LES) in June 1916. The unit's purpose was to coordinate loans of university library material to high schools and other local organizations within the state. In addition to simply loaning material, LES gradually expanded the scope of its operation to include a variety of highly specialized services. Packets of selected items on special subjects, frequently related to high school debate topics, were prepared and distributed. Other specialized materials included plays and children's books, the children's project being funded for many years by the Children's Fund of Michigan. The unit also sponsored workshops and travelling exhibits.
Library Extension Service established a number of branch libraries throughout the state, usually connected with another university outreach program. In particular branch libraries were established to supplement the program of the Extension Service. Increasingly, the primary responsibility of LES was to make available material for the Extension Service's courses. Specialized materials such as plays and children's books were excluded from the LES holdings in the early 1970s.
The Library Extension Services' collection dates from 1916 to 1980. It is divided into two series, an administrative file and unit publications. The administrative file (1916-1980) is arranged alphabetically, one exception being historical material that has been grouped together at the beginning of the series. Included in the series is a nearly complete run of annual reports and information regarding branch libraries. Information regarding the Detroit branch is particularly extensive, and includes a number of annual reports (1959-1980). There is information regarding a cooperative project sponsored by the University of Michigan, Michigan State University and Western Michigan University in the Saginaw area (ca. 1967). The series also contains several folders of information regarding a Special Committee re Cooperative Services of the Michigan Library Association (1960-1967).
The Publications series (1919-1979), has been supplemented by material collected previously by the Bentley Library and represents all of the publications of LES available at the Bentley. Included are the LES Bulletin of Information (1919-1920 to 1952), recommended books for secondary school libraries (1931-1952), alumni reading lists (1931-1948), and bibliographies on selected subjects (ca. 1975-ca. 1979).
The Photographs series includes images showing staff, exhibitions and other activities of the Library Extension Service and views of the library facilities.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Extension Service.; University of Michigan. Library.; University of Michigan. Library Extension Service.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Books.; Children.; Children's Fund of Michigan.; Exhibitions.; Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies.; Libraries--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Administrative File
  - Historical Material
    - Printed, 1956 (Box 1)
    - Documents, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Annual and monthly reports
    - 1916-1930 (Box 1)
    - 1930-1939 (Box 1)
    - 1939-1945 (Box 1)
    - 1945-1950 (Box 1)
    - 1951-1955 (Box 1)
    - 1955-1960 (Box 1)
    - 1961-1965 (Box 1)
    - 1965-1967 (Box 1)
    - 1967-1968 (includes departmental reorganization) (Box 1)
    - 1968-1973 (Box 1)
    - 1975-1980 (monthly only) (Box 1)
  - Children's Fund of Michigan,1930-1954 (Box 1)
  - Conference Center Committee,1958 (Box 1)
  - Conference Division,1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence,1974-1977 (Box 1)
  - Department space inventory,1969 (Box 1)
  - Divisional Libraries Clerical meetings,1975 (Box 1)
  - Fisher Memorial Collection,1950-1954 (Box 1)
  - Form letters and general instructions,1945-1953 (Box 1)
  - Dearborn subsidy,1971 (Box 1)
  - Detroit branch
    - Annual Reports
      - 1944-1958 (Box 1)
      - 1959-1965 (Box 1)
      - 1968-19T5 (Box 1)
      - 1975-1980 (Box 1)
    - General,1969-1978
      - Manual for Library circa 1951 (Box 1)
  - Fresh Air Camp branch,1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Grand Rapids branch
    - 1959-1968 (Box 1)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Library Association, Special Committee re Cooperative Services
    - 1960-1966, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Correspondence,1960-1967 (Box 1)
  - National Music Camp (Interlochen) branch, 1951-1954 1959-1972 (Box 1)
  - Reports,miscellaneous,1959-1971 (Box 1)
  - Saginaw projects circa 1967 (Box 1)
- Publications
  - Library Extension Service Bulletin of Information,1919-1920 to 1952 (Box 1)
  - Books for Secondary School Libraries (various titles),1931-1952 (Box 1)
    (published irregularly)
  - Alumni Reading Lists: 1931, 1934, 1939, 1942, 1948 (Box 1)
  - Bibliographies circa 1975-1979 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous publications (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Photos, 3 folders (Box 1)